Free from his pain
고통을 덜어 줘
Cut his hair
저자의 머리카락을 잘라
We will go back to KORYO
고려로 간다
I will return it to his hometown
반드시 고향집에 전해주마
Ziyi Zhang
장쓰이
Rong Guang Yu
위롱광
Stop!
멈춰라
They say, the castle is too disordered...
황성을 짓느라 성내가 아주 복잡해서
they will lead us to the temporary reception hall
임시로 지은 회동관으로 모시겠답니다
Here is too large
임시로 지은 회동관이 생각보다 커 보입니다
This place does not look like a reception hall Let me find out
여긴 객사처럼 보이지 않습니다 제가 알아보죠
General, behave honorably
장군 정중히 예를 갖춰서 행동하시오
lam General CHOI Jung of Yongho troop, the protectors of the Koryo's envoys
고려 용호군 최정이오
Where is the MING's officials to greet us?
사신단을 맞이하는 자들은 어디 있소?
Remove your weapons and official attires!
죄인들은 무기를 버려라
KORYO murdered our diplomatic envoy
너희가 명나라의 사신을 죽이고도
then keep dispatching spies
수시로 첩자를 보내더니
Now, you send us a military in the name of the envoys
이젠 사행을 구실로 병사까지 보내?
Don't panic, and stop moving
당황하지 말고 그대로 있어
Stay back
넌 나서지 마라
Throw your weapons away Anyone to disobey I will slash him!
무기를 버려라 거역하는 자는 당장 벨 것이다
General CHOI!
최장군
General, Don't
그러면 아니됩니다.
My duty is protecting the envoys
내 임무는 사신단을 지키는 겁니다
General CHOI Jung!
최정 장군
Everyone, follow what they said
모두들.… 저들의 뜻에 순순히 따르거라
General!
장군!
we are almost in the exile
이제 얼마 남지가 않았답니다
Sorry for my impertinent
제가 혈기를 부린 탓에 .…
It's my fault---
송구스럽습니다
No, it is our destiny for imprisonment
어차피 투옥될 운명이었소
Exile is better than in prison
답답한 지하감옥에 같혀있느니.…
suffocating prison--- This is better---
차라리 귀향지가 더 자유스럽지
but here is
그런데 여긴.…
too hot. Ugh!
너무 덤구만.… 억!
Hello
안녕하세요
We are from KORYO
우린 고려사람입니다
We were in the middle of exile, by MING
주원장이 우릴 귀양 보냈소!
Are you a general from YUAN the MONGOL imperial?
당신들이 용맹하기로 이름 높은.…
the great Cokotemure's cavalry!
원나라 쿠쿠테무르님의 기병대군요!
General, no--- do not step forward this time Don't be offensive
장군 이번엔 나서지 마시오 저들의 비위를 거스르지 말고
We don't have any grudge against the KORYO
우리는 고려인과 아무런 원한이 없다
but we cannot keep alive these MING's dogs!
허나 주원장의 개들은 하나도 살려둘 수 없다
Leave the KORYO’'s fate in their own hands. Let's go!
저들의 운명은 저들에게 맡긴다 가자
eneral, including the ambassador and a general Seh, we have 12 casualties and 23 survivors
장군님 정사님과 서장관을 비롯해 죽은 자가 12인 생존자는 23인
among survivors, five are severely injured
그 중 다섯은 부상이 심합니다
Have everyone gather here!
다 모이게 해
How about preparing to camp out here?
먼저 야영준비를 시키는 것이 어떻겠소?
Since the ambassador died we cannot carry the duty of the envoys anymore
정사님이 안계시니 더 이상 사신단의 책무를 집행 할 수 없습니다
Now, such responsibility O
이제 책임은 부사인 내게 있소이다
If we stay here the MING troops will come
이 곳에 있으면 란저우의 명군이 나타날 것이오
-We then explain whole story to them--- -You want to keep the exile journey again?
-그들에게 자초지종을 고하고. -다시 귀양길에 오르실 검니까?
We should not go off our exile path
귀양행로를 벗어나선 아니되오
Let's follow what MING ordered. Anyway, we are the envoys of the country
우린 죄인이기 이전에 한 나라의 사신이오
We don't bring any official letter and flag. How can we prove our credibility?
국서도 빼앗기고 깃발도 사라졌는데 사신임을 뭘로 증명합니까?
Besides, MING troops might blame us as murderer, instead of Mongols
더구나 명군을 만나면 살인죄를 뒤집어 쓸지도 모릅니다
General, we caught the stangers
별장님 붙잡았습니다
Here is two
두 마립니다
The duty of the Protector troops end now Get ready to leave, immediately!
이제 용호군의 임무는 끝났다
-Get ready to leave, immediately! -Yes sir!
-즉시 떠날 채비 해라 -예
Here is an endless desert
여기는 끝없는 사막이오
Where are we going?
도대체 어디를 갈 수 있단 말이오?
To KORYO!
고려로 갑니다
General, three are missing the others are all injured
장군님 실종된 자가 세 사람 모두 부상자들입니다
Find water and food at first
물과 식량부터 찾아
Hey, Interpreter!
-으으으악! -역관님!
We must hurry and leave We all die if we stay here!
빨리 여기서 나가야 해 여기 있으면 다 죽어
-Wake up! Hold your mind! -Let me out, let me out!!
-정신 좀 차리시라우요 -되! 으악!
We are leaving
이동한다
General, we should look for the missing first
장군님 실종 된 자들을 잠시 찾아 보시는게.…
This trip is too hard for me
나 같은 노구에겐 너무 힘이 드는구나
l always wanted to be buried at my home
죽더라도 고향땅에 묻히고 싶었는데.…
Are you in much pain?
많이 힘드십니까?
Would you rest here for a while?
실 여유가 있겠소?
No
없습니다
Even if we make it to Shandong we still need a boat
다행히 산동까지 간다해도 배가 필요할텐데
It is not about time you worried
지금 걱정 할 일이 아니죠
Get up
일어나십시오
What are you doing?
뭐야
YEESOL
여솔아
General, please forgive my man
장군 저 아일 용서해 주시오
He is a foolish one--- He just wants to care for me
어리석은 놈이 날 위한답시고.…
He is a slave of the vice-ambassador
부사맥에서 따라온 노비입니다
This is the Great Wall connecting to the east
이게 동쪽으로 이어지는 장성입니다
It is where the MING and the YUAN are at battle
명군과 원군이 전쟁중인 곳이죠
Below are villages where the MING troops are based
아래쪽에는 마을들이 있고 알다시피 명군의 거점입니다
Avoid the village and the MING troops
마을과 명군도 피해간다
Let's eliminate any chance to meet anyone
-누구와도 마주쳐선 안돼 -장군님!
General, if we head towards the north we must confront YUAN's troops
북쪽으로 가게 되면 원군과 마주 칠 수 밖에 없습니다
What about here in the middle?
여기! 가운데 사막을 지나면 되겠군
It's impossible It's a desert of death
불가능합니다
In the daytime, everything is burned
한낮엔 불덩이처럼 달귀지고
Also, it takes at least twenty days to cross
걸어선 족히 스무날도 넘게 걸립니다
Besides, our remaining food and water will last only 6 days
더구나 남은 식량과 물도 엿새치 정도뿐입니다
To that place
여기까지
we will cross within ten days
열흘에 걷는다
If necessary we will eat once a day and walk during the mid-night
필요하다면 하루에 한번씩 먹고 밤에도 계속 걷는다
in that case, southern desert is better we can gain three or four days
그렇다면 남쪽 영역을 질러가죠 사나흘은 벌겁니다
Whose territory is that?
거긴 누구 영역이냐?
that is an abandon land No one could conquer the area
이곳은 불모지라 누구도 장악하지 못했을겁니다
However, my concern is the vice-ambassador
다만 부사님이 걱정입니다
-He is already exhausted -No one here free from suffer!
-지금의 행군도 견디기 힘드신데… -힘들지 않은 자 여기 없어
From now on, you guide us
앞으론 니가 길잡이 노릇을 해라
Don't block our march
행군을 멈추게 하지 마라
Whoever bothers our way will die by my sword!
가차없이 벨 것이다
Son of bitch!
개 백정 같으니…
He makes us human fry. He will kill us
우릴 다 태워 쥐일라고 염병쓰고 있구만 기래
Did you called me?
부르셨습니까?
As a vice-ambassador, I'm ashamed lam in such a wretched state
명색이 부사인 자가 이 모양이니 부끄럽소
Take care of the group
맞으로의 여정을 잘 부탁하오
I hope you all safely return to home....
모두들 고향에 무사히 돌아가기를…
I see
알겠습니다
One thing that I must say
한 가지 해 둘 말이 있어요
This man here
여기 이 아이 말이오
He is not a slave anymore
이후로는 더 이상 노비가 아니오
As I set him free, he is a freeman Treat him accordingly
이제 자유로운 신분이 됐으니 그렇게들 알고 대해 주시오
Please get some sleep
피곤하실텐데 주무십시오
Hey you, stop there!
이 놈들 그 자리에 서
He stole the food while standing guard
장군님 보초를 서면서 병자를 홈졌습니다
Sorry, sir
정말 부끄러운 짓을 했습니다. 장군님!
Please forgive me
한 번만 용서해 주세요 장군님
No mercy to a thief in the battle
전시에 도적질한 자는 용서 할 수 없다
The same goes for one who is taken
군량을 간 수 못한 자 역시 마찬가지…
Beat them twenty floggings each
장 이십대씩 쳐라
Our Joojin troops only eat one piece a day We are equal to your Yongho troops
우리 주진군은 하루 한 덩이 밖에 못 먹고 있수다
I will receive the floggings instead of him!
장철 대신 내 맞갔수다
Do what he wants
되뒤
All right. You, receive all floggings for both
그럼 니가 저들의 매를 모두 맞아라
Watch carefully!
모두 똑똑히 봐뒤
You'd served in many battles with my father
자년 내 아버님과 전쟁을 많이 치지
Am I quite different to him?
아버님과 난 많이 다른가?
The times were not as difficult as now
지금같은 어려움은 별로 없었습니다
But I am sure you will do well, sir
하지만 장군님은 잘 해 내실 검니다.
Will we make it safely reach at Shandong?
산동까지 무사히 갈 수 있을까
Even if we return to KORYO, people scoff at--
고려에 돌아간다해도 모두가 비웃을거야
I failed to protect the envoys I even failed to enter the castle of Nanjing
사신단을 지키지도 못했고 남경성엔 발도 못 디덧으니까
Here you go
이거 받아
Use when you need it
요긴 할 때 써라
Take it
어서 받아
In this situation, dying is better
그래 차라리 뒤지는게 속 편하디
The vice-ambassador disappeared!
부사님이 안 보이십니다
Stop him and search what he brings
놈을 세우고 부사님을 살펴보아라
The vice-ambassador has passed away!
돌아가셨습니다
Bury the body The horse will belong to Yongho troops
시신을 매장해! 말은 용호군이 맡는다
You may bury him yourself but we will take the horse
부사님은 니 손으로 묻어도 좋다 하지만 말은 가져가겠다
General
장군님!
Keep follow the line Stop all!
대오를 이탈하지 마라 모두 멈취라
Good afternoon?
안녕하세요
Please give us water and food
물과 먹을 것을 마련해 주시오
I cannot distinguish who you are
말투를 들어선 어디 사람인지 모르겠구만
What should I do? Should I tell them that we are the KORYO's envoys
어떻게 하죠 사실대로 고려사신이라고 할까요?
Don't do that They don ‘t believe us anyway
하지 말게 믿지도 않을테니
If you want to eat you should pay for it!
배가 고프면 돈을 먼저 내 놓아야지
-What are they saying, bastard? -Do something. We're starving
-뭐라고 하는 거야 저놈들.… -빼고파 죽겠네. 정말!
-Tell something--- -Calm down!
-말좀해봐유 -가만 있어
I cannot bear!
난 못 참것어!
if you move one more step then I'll kill you right now
움직이면 단칼에 베겠다
Would you be from KORYO?
고려에서 오셨소?
Monk, are you also from KORYO?
스님도 고려에서 오셨습니까?
Sir, serve food to these people I will pay for it
주인장 음식을 나뉘주시오 돈은 내가 치르겠소
lam quite obliged lama general, CHOI Jung
고많습니다 용호군의 장군 최정입니다
My Buddhist name is Jisan lam glad to have company on the way home
소승의 법명은 지산 고향 가는 길동무가 생겨 다행입니다
You, thief. How dare you touch my property?
이 도둑놈이 어디 귀한 활을 함부로 손대
Uh? You're a Mongolian soldier!
어! 몽고군이야
Sir
별장!
How come you bring a Mongolian sword?
네가 어떻게 몽고족의 칼을 갖고 있냐?
General!
장군님!
A few days ago, we passed the battlefields
우연히 전장터를 지나왔고
There were only the dead there
거긴 죽은 자들 뿐이었소
..Are you a Buddhist monk? Yes
-넌 승려나? -그렇소
Do you know how to hold ceremony for the dead?
제를 올릴 줄 아는가?
Yes, I learned the Buddhist incantations as well
율종을 배운자 불사를 할 수 있습니다
Would you write down the name of the dead?
시주께서 망자의 이름을 써 주시면 됩니다
All my men were brave warriors
내 부하들은 모두 용맹한 전사였다
Just write The sons of the blue wolf
그냥 '푸른눅대의 아들'이라 써라
Treat the injured first
먼저 부상병들을 치료해
The General is coming
장군님 오셨습니까
Have some, Princess
공주!
Would you keep refusing food?
계속해서 아무것도 먹지 않을건가?
Did you hear that he called her princess?
방금 공주라고 한 말 들었어요?
"Escape me"
"구해주세요"
my friend, what do you wish for?
친구 뭘 원해?
Shit! Who bring this filthy thing in here?
썩은 시체를 여기 버려둔 놈이 누구야?
You bring this thing here, didn't you?
네 놈 짓이지?
Get rid of it, right now
당장 이 더러운걸 치우지 못해?
Don't kill him
죽이지는 마라
He's a real fighter with spears!
오랜만에 뛰어난 창술을 보는군
Where are you from?
너는 어디서 왔느나?
Don't move. We might lose everything
잘못하면 감당할 수 없는 일이 벌어진다
he YUAN troops and the Central Asians are the confederates. They might kill us all
원군과 색목인은 모두가 한패요 우리 모두를 죽일 수도 있어
He has the eyes of a lion
놈은 사자의 눈을 가졌어
I want to make him as my man
내 사람으로 만들고 싶다
General he already killed five of our men
장군님 이놈이 우리 애들을 다섯이나 죽였습니다
I will give you ten horses in return
말 열필을 주마
You've buried this strange place You met with a wrong place and time. God bless you!
불충한 나라, 불운한 시운을 만나 이국만리 유골만 묻히셨군요
If you insist on the difficult path I will joint you
장군일행이 굳이 험로를 택하겠다면 소승도 동행하겠소
No need for that
그러실 필요 없습니다
lam familiar with these locations and might be help to you
여기서부턴 길을 조금 아니 다소 도움이 될겁니다
Now we finished to bury Shall we leave now?
매장이 끝났습니다 출발하시죠
We should wait here
여기서 기다린다
The YUAN troops will pass through this place
원군도 일단은 이 길을 지날 것이다
we will save the princess!
공주를 구한다
Don't you say that we are heading towards KORYO sir?
저희 목적은 고려로 돌아가는거라 하지 않았습니까
That was my intention until yesterday
어제까지는 그랬지
However, we are the diplomatic envoys
하지만 우린 사신단이다
If we help the MING dynasty we could enter the castle of Nanjing with grand welcome
명황실을 도우면 성대한 환대를 받으면서 남경에 입성 할 수있어
It won't be late for us to return home after that
그런 연후에 돌아가도 늦지 않아
a reckless plan! YUAN troops are the strongest one in the world
무모합니다 저들은 누구보다 강력한 원의 기병이요
Please reconsider General
다시 한 번 생각해 보십시오
I made my decision during whole night
밤새 고민해서 결정했어
Let's try
해보죠
Daejung!
대정
We have to save Yeesol man as well
그 애도 구해야 합니다
We will attack them on both sides The Yongho troops and I will attack from the bottom
일시에 협공한다 나와 용호군은 위에서 밑으로
You with others ambush them from another side
별장은 나머지를 인솔해 아래에서 매복한다
-Now go -Shit, no! They are coming right there
-내려가라 -다 틀렸어. 저기 옵니다
We will attack them all together!
좋아 한꺼번에 공격한다
General, we don't have any chance to win
장군님 승산이 없습니다
We can do it
구할 수 있어
General
장군
All hide yourselves
모두 몸을 낮춰
Daejung!
대정!
Now is our chance
지금이다
Attack the horses first
말을 먼저 공격해라
Save the Princess
공주를 지켜라
Interpreter, Interpreter, sir... Go away get away from me I say
-역관님, 역관님.… -저리가, 저리가, 안가…
what an idiot
저 바보같은 자식.…
lam General CHOI Jung to protect the KORYO's envoys
고려사신으로 온 용호군 장군 최정입니다
Get up
일어나시오
The emperor calls me princess Buyong
황제께서는 날 부용공주라 부르죠
You do not look like the envoys
헌데 사신들처럼 보이진 않는군요
I also thought a princess lived in the palace your highness
저도 공주님은 항상 황궁에 계신 출 알았습니다
Take me to the castle of Nanjing as soon as possible
난 당장 남경으로 가야해요
If you safely escort me at there the emperor will award you greatly
날 호위 해 주면 큰상을 내리겠소
We did save you, now we are responsible for you to protect as well
공주님을 구한 제가 당연히 보호 합니다
Your highness
공주님!
board the carriage without any worries
걱정말고 마차에 오르십시오
It is our total victory, sir
우리가 완벽하게 이겼습니다
Are you 0k?
다친데는 없어요?
hey you! You said you are an interpreter, aren't you?
이봐 역관이라 했느냐?
lam PARK Jumyung Il haven't entered official post yet
박주명입니다 아직은 품외 벼슬이지만 머잖아.……
-but sooner or later I will enter--- -Deliver my words
내 말을 전해라
to that man in black
검은 옷을 입은 저자에게 ..
Hey! The princess wants you to guard her carriage
이 봐 공주님이 너한테 마차 호위를 부탁하는데
Sir, the princess wants that man to guard the carriage
공주가 저 아이한테 호위를 부탁하는데요
I will give you a mission
너에게 임무를 내리겠다
Guard the princess carriage
공주의 마차를 호위해라
I will go to see the place where master is buried
주인님께서 묻힌 곳을 보러 갈 겁니다
You can talk--- you can talk---
말하네! 말하는구만 응?
lam ordering you again guard the carriage
다시 명령한다. 마차를 호위해라
lam a free man now I will do as I please
난 자유인이오 내 맘대로 하겠소
General, don't be upset
장군님 고정하십시오
I don't need a slave who forgot his place
본분을 잊고 날뛰는 노비는 필요없어
But the vice-ambassador has set him free, sir
부사께서 양인으로 만들어주셨습니다
He was out of mind on the brink of death
돌아가시기 직전이라 정신이 혼미한 상태였어
Once is a slave will be forever a slave That is the law of KORYO!
노비로 태어난 자는 명원한 노비야 그게 고려의 법이다
Stop it
그만 뒤요
We will leave this bastard here
놈을 두고 간다
Everyone, mount your own horses
모두 말에 올라
General, there is one girl who has survived
장군님 계집 하나가 살았습니다
She is a Chinese slut. Leave her behind
오랑캐 창녀야 두고가
General, mercy is the virtue of the great man
장군 자비는 윗사람의 덕목이오
This is not any of your concern All decisions will be mine
스님이 나설 문제가 아닙니다 모든 결정은 이 행군을 책임진 저의 입니다
Take all with us
모두 데리고 가요
General
장군님!
The general is coming
장군이 돌아왔다
Honorable Cookoo
쿠쿠님 공주를.…
I lost the princess of MING
놓졌습니다
KOROY took her...
고려인들에게 빼앗겼…
Lay him down at my tent
내 파오 안에 눔혀라
Princess
공주님!
It may be below you, but please eat this
보잘 것 없지만 드십시오
I didn't have time to say this---
아까는 미처 말을 못했는데.…
Thank you
고마워요
Please get some rest, your highness
편히 쉬십시오
I'm Yooran
난 유란이예요
Yooran?
유란?
meaning of a dancing orchid?
여기저기 노니는 난초라.…
That is the most beautiful name I've ever heard
지금까지 들은 이름 중 가장 예쁜 이름이야
lam PARK Jumyung
난 박주명이라고 해
You have cute eyes
눈이 참 귀엽네요
You wicked one! As a person of the envoys
요망스런 것들!
you don't have any regret in this predicament
사행을 대변하는 자로서 일을 이 지경에 만든 책임을 느끼지는 못하고
play with a woman instead
계집과 농짓거리를 해
What responsibilities do I carry?
아니 내가 뭘 책임져야 되는데요?
lam just an interpreter
난 그냥 역관일 뿐입니다
How come you regret at all These miscellaneous readings are in vain
잡문께나 읽었다는 자가 반성 할 줄도 모르느나?
what?
뭐요?
you are the one who ruined the country and accumulated wealth in Buddhist temple---
나라를 망치고도 권력을 탐하고 축제만 일삼는 사찰에서는
How dare you mention the Confucius as miscellaneous readings?
공맹의 도를 일컬어서 잡문이라고 합니까
What an egotistic views the Confucius is best
개명세상을 꿈꾸는 것이
Hope for wonderful world is in every teaching
너희 유가만의 발상이란게 대체 어디서 나온 아집이나?
The Confucius's words were spread all over the world
주자의 글을 읽는 소리가 온 천지에 울려 퍼져갑니다
Open your eyes you should know the principles of the world?
세상 돌아가는 이치를 어찌 그리 모르십니까
The first time I made a love was under the full moon
제가 처음 사고를 친 건 대보름날이었어요
She was sixteen, I was eighteen
솔매가 열 여섯 난 열여더요
Every evening we met on the hills
우린 매일 밤 뒷산에서 만났어요
Then one day, she became pregnant
그러다 솔매가 아이를 가졌고요
and we got married Five days later, l was gone on an expedition
그래서 곧 혼례를 올리고 닷새만에 출정하게 되었어요
Was it a son or a daughter?
그것이 아들이여 딸이여?
When I left, she was eight months pregnancy she might give a birth now
떠나올 때 여달 만삭이었으니깐 낳았겠죠
I miss my wife so much
근데요 색시가… 더 보고 싶네요
Is he ok?
그 사람 좀 어떠냐?
Get some sleep. I will take care of him
너희들은 그만 자라 내가 돌볼테니
Tomorrow, he can recover, your highness
품자면 내일부터 말을 탈 수 있습니다
Where are you heading?
당신들은 어디로 가죠?
To KORYO, your highness
고려로 갑니다
The general team and yours seem not get along well
서로 사이가 안좋아 보여요
In this kind of long journey many things might happen
여러 사람이 먼길을 가다 보면 그렇게 보일 수 있죠
Take good care of him
잘 보살펴주세요
Thank you, your highness
예 감사합니다
Do not worry about the vice ambassador
부사님 걱정은 마라
He was buried the place open to sunshine
별이 잘 드는 곳에 모셨어
Do you have any family at home?
고향에 가족은 있나?
lam alone
난 혼잡니다
From now on, you are not alone
맞으론 혼자라고 생각마라
We will go together
함께가자
until KORYO
고려까지
MING'II seek every corner for princess
주원장이 사방으로 공주를 찾을검니다
we must head north
어서 북상해야 합니다
Get out, everyone I have something to talk with Rambulhwa
모두 나가있어라 람불화와 할 말이 있다
Do me a favor
내 부탁을 들어다오
Please name it
말씀하십시오
MING kidnapped my sister I want to take revenge on MING's princess
내 누이를 납치한 주원장을 응징하겠다
Bring her in front of me
반드시 공주를 잡아와라
Why did you help me?
왜 날 도왔죠?
You might have resent the MING Empire for exile
명나라는 당신들을 귀양 보냈잖아요
Personal concerns and the public affair That ’s two different issues
개인과 나라의 일을 다릅니다
If you help us see the emperor
공주가 황제님을 배알토록 해 주시면
I can resolve the misunderstanding about our envoys
우리 사신단에 오해도 풀릴겁니다
What is the name of that man walking behind?
저 뒤에 오는 사람 이름이 뭐죠?
He is a just slave, your highness
노비입니다
l asked his name
난 저 사람 이름을 물었어요
They're coming
쫓아와유
They're after us
거시기들이 쫓아와유
Where are they now?
어디쯤 오고 있느나?
They're moving really fast, sir
무..무지하게 빨라유
How many are they?
몇 명쯤이나 되지?
Over a hundred, sir
한 백명도 넘는 것 같아유
We don't have much time We have to leave at once
지체할 시간이 없습니다 여길 떠나야 합니다
We cannot avoid them What can we do, General?
장군 어쩌면 좋겠소?
We'll lure them to the carriage
마차로 유인한다
That's good idea, sir
그거 정말 좋은 생각입니다
Who will carry this carriage
기카몬 마차는 뉘기래 몸니까
il do
제가 맡겠습니다
Give me two soldiers of Yongho troop
용호군 둘을 붙여주십시오
No, in this time, drive it by the person who didn't fight
그동안 싸우지 않았던 자가 마차를 몬다
no, no I'm just an interpreter
저는 그냥 역관일 뿐 입니다
And I never drove a carriage before
그리고 전 한번도 마차를 몰아 본 적이 없는데…
He is too young, sir
저 아인 아직 어린앰니다
It has been decided
이미 결정 난 일이야
How come it's always us, the Joojin soldiers?
어케 맨날 주진군이야요
Why do you keep quiet, captain?
형님 그저 보고만 있을 검니까
He even didn ‘t know his baby
쟈는유 아직 태어난 애기도.…
Someone has to drive the carriage
누군간 마차를 몰아야 돼
Put that boy on the carriage
저 아이를 마차에 태워
Daejung Captain
대정님.…
We'll make them think the princess is in the carriage
공주가 타고 있는 것처럼 보여야 합니다
Wear it
입어라
Please help me
도와주세요
-You can help me, can't you? -lam sorry
-날 도와 줄 수 있잖아요 -미안해요
Let me go with you
같이 가자
Make a detour on the mountain, after that’ you can see the Hwangho River
산맥을 우회하면 황하가 보일거야
We will wait for you there
거기서 너희들을 기다리고 있겠다
Please take these, return to the master ’s family
저 대신 주인님 택에 전해 주십시오
We will meet
거기서 만나자
Take care of Dansaeng
단생일 잘 부탁한다
You go for the princess
넌 나를 위해 가는거야
Never forget your duty is to protect the princess. It's me
공주를 지키는게 너의 임무임을 잊지마
Be sure, you return to me
반드시 돌아와라
Stop
멈춰라
We will walk from here
여기서부터 걷는다
Put together your horses for them not to discover us
놈들이 발견하지 못하게 말 을 한 곳에 묶어라
What if Dansaeng doesn't come back?
단생이가 못 돌아오은 어떡하지?
The Mongolians are not stupid. They ‘Il come after us sooner or later
몽고군은 어리석지 않네 곧 우릴 쫓아 올걸세
I'll be right behind you
금방 따라 가겠습니다
The princess isn't in the carriage
마차에는 공주가 없어
There can't be only one soldier guarding her
단 한명이 호위 할 리 없다
They are heading for the Hwangho river to crosse the mountain
산맥을 넘어 황하로 향했군요
If so, it's impossible for us to find them
그렇다면 찾기란 불가능합니다
They eventually will cross the Hwangho river
어차피 그들은 황하를 건너야 한다
Burn all village and the ferry beyond the mountain
나루터와 인근마을을 모두 불태운다
so make nobody cross the river
한 놈도 황하를 건너지 못하게 해라
yes!
예!!
What about him?
저 놈은요?
follow and kill him
쫓아가 없애
Hurry, lets go
빨리 가자
It's the Mongolian soldiers
몽고군이야
Dansaeng
단생
Throw that robe away and run. Now
당신도 그 옷을 벗고 달아나요. 어서!
Go, now! Hurry, run
도망가요 어서
Go! And run
도망가요 어서, 어서
Yeosol
형
lam so sorry
잘못했어
Get up
일어나
Il served two years against the north
북계에서 2년
and two years to fighting the Japanese
남녁에 내려가 왜놈과 싸우느라고 2년
Altogether it was four years in the military
내 4년이 넘어 돌와왔수다
When I got back only rat shit was in the kitchen
개랬더니 집구석엔 먹을 거라고는 쥐새끼똥뿐입디다
Shit! So I went to the head officer
에라 쌍! 그래 능주를 확 퍼먹구서
and hit him with my head, bang
병리장을 찾아가 기냥 마쁘로 본시떼 놓고 받았쑤다
So did they force you to choose between imprisonment or military service?
그랬더니 옥살이와 군역중에서 하나 골라라 하던가?
How did you know that?
어케 아셨수까?
It is so obvious
군역을 할당하는 향리들 수작이야 뻔하지 뭐
Don't go back at all
아예 돌아가지 말게
I heard that there is a KORYO village in Beijing
대두에는 고려촌도 있다던데
I will go back no matter what
꼭 갈꺼외다
My wife is waiting for me
우리 애미나이가 기다리니끼니…
Guess your wife is awfully pretty?
자네 마누라가 예쁜가 보네?
She is like a fat bear
뭐 미련 곰탱이 같이 생겼지 뭐
Yet, for me, she is the prettiest one in the world tH] HC}
기래도 하는 짓거리 보면 양구비보다 더 곱지 않같써
What about you? Don't you miss your wife?
하일인 색시 안 보고프니?
How many times do I have to tell you? I'm not married, yet
몇 번을 말하 장가 안 갔어. 아즉.…
I see
그렇디…
What happen?
어떻게 됐나
As we expected
예상했던 대롭니다
Sir, come
오셨어요
Be patient, even if it may be freezing That is if you don't want to call the Mongolian troops
춤더라도 참아 몽고군을 부르고 싶지 않으면
It was not my intention to wake you up. l apologize, your highness
잠을 깨워 죄송합니다
I had a dream
꿈을 는데.…
I was already in the Royal Palace
황궁에 있었어요
Once we cross the Hwangho river, we will escort you to the castle of Nanjing
황하를 건너면 남경으로 모실 검니다
Daejung tells me that this group is heading towards Shandong
진대정 말론 산동으로 간다던데요
Believe me. I will keep my word, your highness
공주님과 약속은 꼭 지키겠습니다
Does the carriage return to us?
마차는 돌아올까요?
lam sure it will do, your highness
돌아올겁니다
They aren't here, sir
여긴 없습니다
Divide the soldiers into smaller groups and search them each area
병사를 분산하여 공주를 찾아라
What about the people here?
이 자들은 어떻게 할까요?
We should kill them as they have seen us
우리를 보았으니 살려 둘 수 없다
Not a single soul is at the ferry
나루터인데 인적이 없군요
check again for sure
한 번 살펴봐야겠습니다
Why aren't we going down?
왜 내려가지 않죠?
first we will move under the valley
일단 저쪽 계곡으로 이동한다
Ha-il
하일
Go round to check and return
다녀오너라
What is it?
어케 됐네
the enemy are hiding near the ferry
거시기들이유 나루터 근처에 숨어가지구유
Kill everyone who tries to cross the river
강을 건널라구 하는 사람들을 기냥 죄다 죽이구있시유
It seems that we have to give up Dungju as well as Nanjing
이젠 등주도 남경도 포기해야 돼
Who are they, huh?
뭐야 저거 엉?
I didn't have any intention
거시기 지가유.…
to bring them here
거 데리고 올려구 한 건 아니구유
They just followed me from the ferry
나루터에서부터 계속 졸졸 따라오면서.…
Now, the YUAN troops will find us any moment
이제 원병들이 금방 찾겠구만
We should have kicked them out then
기럼 다 쫓아버려야지
stop
모두 그만 뒤
Stop it
멈춰라
Don't you hear the word, ‘stop’ ?
멈추라는 말 안들리나
I never thought I would see you here, your highness
공주님을 보게 될 줄은 정말 몰랐습니다
I have something to discuss with both of you
저…… 두 분께 긴히 드릴 말씀이…
Let's cross the river when a night falls
밤을 이용해서 강을 건너세
Yes-- it is too far to Dungju
따지고 보면 등주까지는 너무 멈니다
It would be better to go to Balhae Bay and find a ferry boat there
차라리 발해만 쪽으로 가서 나릇배라도 구하는게 날 검니다
Are you saying that we should cross the sea by a ferry boat?
아니 지금 나릇배를 타고 바다를 건너자는 겐가?
If you can pass through the YUAN cavalry, then go by yourself
원기병을 둘고 가려면 스님 혼자 가슈
after crossing the Hwangho river
아니 황하를 넘은 다음에
What if does the general insist on escort the princess to the castle of Nanjing then?
장군이 공주하고 같이 남경까지 가자면 어찔꺼요
Are you crazy? We have to return to KORYO
미졌수 여까지 우리가 와 왔는데
In fact, the princess brings us all problems
사실 모든 문제는 공주와 함께 있기 때문아닙니까
Besides, now it seems we have to take all those people along as well
게다가 저 떨거지까지 함께 딸려 올 것 같은데.…
We have a good news
좋은 소식이 있다
Five days later, we'll meet the fortress on the coast where the MING troops are based
닷새정도 동쪽 숲으로 가면 명군이 주둔하는 해안토성이 있어
The princess says if we escort her and her people there
공주가 거기까지 자기와 한족을 호위해 주면
she will arrange for us a boat, which will take us to KORYO
고려로 가는 배를 주겠다고 했다
Let us accept her offer
제안을 받아들이자
Do we wait for the carriage, don't you?
저… 마차 올 때까지는 기다릴 거죠
Do you think they will come back alive?
돌아올 수 있다고 생각하나
Nobody go back to KORYO without a boat
배없인 아무도 고려에 못 가
With the MING troops, we are safe enough
명군이 있으면 안전도 보장되고
Also, MING's emperor would know what we help her
자연히 공주를 도운게 황실에 알려지게 된다
The YUAN troops never give the princess up
원병은 공주를 포기하지 않을 검니다
but it is true that we need a boat
하지만 배가 필요한 건 사실입니다
I will follow your opinion, general
장군님 뜻에 따르겠습니다
Good
잘 생각했다
Get up
일어들나라
But
하지만!
we do have to wait for the people who was in carriage
마차 타고 간 사람들을 기다려야 합니다
We all agreed, your highness
모두 동의했습니다
If your decision is out of pity, then return everything back to where it was
만일 동정하는 거라면 그럴 필요 없어요
It is not the time for pity
지금은 서로 동정 할 처지가 못됩니다
Prepare to leave
떠날 준비해라
Stay Joojin troops here
주진군은 앉아있어
You will leave when Yeosol and Dansaeng return
여솔과 단생이가 돌아온 뒤에 떠난다
You've been in the military long enough to know
그 나이 먹도록 군영에 있었으니
what the result of disobey to a general's orders...
장군 명령에 불복하면 어떻게 된다는 건 잘 알겠지?
General
장군님
we should wait until this evening passes
오늘밤까지만 기다려 주십시오
Dansaeng is coming
단생이가 왔시유
You came back alive
살아 왔구만 이거! 응
You're alright? are you 0k?
-괜찮은겨 -괜찮네?
I've been waiting for you so much
당신이 오기만을 기다렸소
Welcome to return
고생 많았다
It stained with the YUAN troops
오랑캐의 피로 더러워졌습니다
lam glad you returned alive
살아 돌아와서 고맘다
I did not wish to award a slave such an honorable death
천한 인간에게 명예로운 죽음을 안겨주고 싶지 않았어
The noble tend to have useless thoughts
귀족들은 쓸데없는 생각을 많이 하는군요
Shouldn't we arrange a horse for the princess?
공주님은 말이라도 타셔야 하지 않소?
She is not the princess of KORYO
고려의 공주가 아닙니다
The princess wants to ride in a palanquin It is out of the question
공주가 가마를 타겠답니다 그게 말이나 됩니까?
Get thick wood, now
묵직한 나무를 빨리 구해
It is foolish
그건 어리석은 짓이오
Daejung
대정
Let's carry it
들자
Hey, captain
아 형님!
Why should we carry that thing
와 우리가 저걸 들고 지랄입네까
Someone has to carry it
누군간 들어야 돼
Hurry
어서
My soles are as parched as the back of a turtle
난 발바닥이 갈라져 거북등 됐수다
We don't have much time
시간이 없어
shit
어휴
I'll carry it
제가 들죠
A the morning mountain at home, white bird sing a song x
겨단풍이 붉게 물든 숲 하얀 새가 노래하네
i l want to hear the song, wish to go back home
껴하얀새의 노래하는 그곳이 나의 고향
idiot! Remember the YUAN troops right behind us
멍청한 것! 원병들이 따라오는 것도 모르느냐
lam sorry
죄송합니다
Your voice is louder than hers, monk
스님 목소리가 더 커요
She's just trying to comfort the children why are you so picky?
아 거 애들 안심시키려는건데 왜 그러십니까
Aren't you worried about the children?
스님은 이 애들 걱정도 안되십니까
If you are that thoughtful, you wouldn't be playing around with the prostitute
그런 사람이 창기와 놀아나는데 정신을 파나
if the YUAN troops catch us those children are the first victims
원병이 쫓아오면 저 애들은 다 죽은 목숨이야
and you are also the first one who runs off
자네는 이미 가장 먼저 도망친 후겠지
What?
뭐라구요?
What do you know about me?
대체 나에 대해 얼마나 안다고 그런 말씀을 하시는 겁니까
Silly one
네 이놈.…
Look at yourself
네 놈이 진정 너란 인간을 모른단 말이냐
We've walked all day, but only come 12 kilometers
온 종일 꼬박 걸었는데도 겨우 삼십리 정도 밖에 못왔어
With this speed it'll take more than twenty days
이렇게 가몬유 스무날도 더 걸려유
Brother, I don't understand at all
내 대갈빠 나빠가지구 당최 모르갔는데
How can be you still alone with this age? no one waiting for you at home?
어케 기다리는 사람이 하나도 없다는 거이 그거이 말이되네
I really don't have anyone. Really
아무도 없어요 정말
Do you have any girl of your heart?
어디 숨겨 논 삭시도 없는겨
HA II, you also miss your wife, don ’t you?
하일이 형도 색시 보고 싶죠 그죠?
He's still a bachelor
저거이 아직 총각이야
How many times I told you?
아니 몇 번을 말하
You haven't sex with a girl, don't you?
너 한번도 못해봤디 못해봤…
why don't you get married until now?
그 나이에 장가 안가셨어요?
I took the wrong pills when he was young
어려서 보약을 한 번 잘못 먹어서 그라
Yeah, he has still a child's
아직 애기여!
Would you like to try this?
이것 좀 먹어 볼래요
No
싫어요
Hey, hey---
어이 어이 할마이
hey granny comes back
할마이 돌아오라우
She is an distracted old lady
정신이 나간 노인입니다
Since her son was killed at the ferry No one can take care of her
나루터에서 아들이 죽고 혼자가 되었지요
How can we care about an old one like her?
지금이 미친 할망구 걱정 할 때예요?
Bring her here. She is also one of my people
데려와라 그녀도 내 백성이다
Who are you? Let me go
어서 내려줘. 나 갈거야!
I'll carry her on my back
제가 업고 갈께유
Tens of soldiers are coming to this way, sir
열 댓명 정도 모두 말을 탕습니다
Did they find us?
우릴 발견한건가
lam afraid so
그럴겁니다
Then let's just take the princess
기럼 공주만 데리고 갑시다
If we take the others along, we'll all die
다 데리고 갔다가는 잡혀죽기 쉽상이디
He's right We'll just take the princess and Yooran
그 말 맞어 공주하고 유란만
We must keep the promise to the princess
공주와의 약속은 지켜야돼
We bring all of them along
끝까지 함께 간다
The YUAN cavalry are faster than the wind
원기병은 바람보다 빨라요
Even a hunter takes care of an animal
산짐승도 비를 피해갔구 헌으로 들픈
who lost their way. That's a basic moral---
돌봐주는 것이 사냥꾼의 거시기에유
I will stay with them if you want to leave without them
저 사람들 내뿔구 가실려은 지는 남을래유
bastard
야이 쌍놈아 새끼야
Don't you miss your mother?
너 오마니 안 볼꺼이네
my ma will be proud of me
엄니도 잘했다고 할꺼여
Let's go together, as far as we can
함께 가보죠 가 볼 때까진
What don't you hurry? The YUAN troops are coming!
들하죠? 원병들이 오는데.…
The princess will start first with the Joojin troops
공주부터 이동한다
Joojin Troops
주진군
Order them to carry the palanquin. Now
가마를 들게 해
quickly
어서
This palanquin is holding us back
한족 보다도 이것 때문에 너무 늦어집니다
General
장군
Are you waiting for the YUAN troops to get us?
원병이 오기를 기다리는 건가요
They ask you for give up the palanquin
공주님이 내리시면 출발하겠답니다
Who said so?
감히 누가 그런 소릴.…
Get out
내려요
Order them to carry my palanquin at once
당장 가마를 들라고 명령해요
Stop
멈춰
The princess will be target by the enemy because of this palanquin
가마 때문에 공주가 놈들의 표적이 될겁니다
The Yongho troops and I will go at them
나와 용호군이 뒤를 맡겠다
Wait here
모두 여기서 기다려
You don ‘t have to go to meet them who are chasing after us
쫓아오는 자들을 일부러 맞으러 갈 필은 없잖습니까
lam the one who makes a decision
결정은 내가 내려
You just follow my orders
너희들은 복종하면 돼
Let's go
가자 !
In the forest, the cavalry have less advantage
숲에선 기병들이 더 불리하다
Let's follow me with same intervals of one meters
서로 20보 간격을 두고 내려간다
If you lost the distances, you will be faced alone on the group of the enemy
간격을 넓히면 한 명이 여과 마주치게 됩니다.
Are you afraid?
두렵나?
Then, stay here until you hear something. You can rush out then
그럼 여길 지키다가 소리가 나면 달려와
I will go down instead of you, general
장군님 대신 제가 내려가겠습니다
Watch the hill
비탈을 지켜!
If they pass through here, the princess will be in great danger
여기가 돌리면 공주가 위험해
On my signal, everyone rush at them
내가 신호하면 동시에 달려든다
Do as I said. You hear?
내가 말한대로 행동한다 알겠지?
Dansaeng
자 단생아 검내지 말고
yes
예
is that you?
별장인가?
We'll take care of here Go and protect the princess
여긴 우리가 맡을 테니 가서 공주를 지켜
Look, the Byuljang is coming
저기 별장님 오시네유!
It is very important. You should deliver it
목숨이 달린 일이니 꼭 전달해야 한다
Please trust my husband
공주님 제 남편을 믿어 주십시오
Now, go
와요!
They are coming
원병이 왔다!
Go, hurry
어서 가!
Be careful
여보, 조심하세요
Move, princess
공주님 빨리 피하세요
There is the princess
공주님이 위험하네
Stand back
다가오지마
Stop it! Don't move
움직이지마! 거기서
Take away your filthy hands, you slave
이 손 놓지 못해! 노비 주제에
You could have killed me! I'm a princess
너 때문에 죽을 뻔 했어 난 공주란 말이야
Stop screaming
소리지르지마
Don't think you can do anything because you are a princess
공주라고해서 누구한테나 함부로 할 수 있다고 생각하지마
Leave me alone
손 치워!
Take this
잡게
Byuljang--- Byuljang
별장.…
How's your feeling?
정신이 드십니까?
What about the Yongho troops?
용호군은?
Help me up
날 일으켜라!
What happened to the enemy?
놈들은 어떻게 됐지?
Daejung wiped out them with the Joojin troops, sir
대정이 주진군을 데리고 전멸시켰습니다
What about the princess?
공주는?
She is coming this way, sir
일루 오고 있는디유!
We will resume the journey We are leaving
휴식을 끝내! 이동한다
It is quite late
밤이 깊었습니다
and you must take rest a bit more, sir
그리고 장군님도 더 쉬셔야합니다
it's better leaving early in the morning, sir
새벽에 출발하는게 좋습니다
I said get up
모두 일어나란 말 안들이나!
If you wish to leave, go yourself, sir
갈라면 먼저가시우!
We will get some rest and then leave
우린 눈 좀 붙히다 가겼수다
I know that you are the agitator
네놈이 조종하고 있다는걸 다 알고 있어
until now, I let you have your own way
이제껏 네 맘대로 행동하는 걸 두고 봤지만
but now I will not tolerate you
이젠 결코 용서 할 수 없어
- Leave him alone - Dochoong, Seat down...
-형님 가만 두지 못허겼어? -도충 앉어!
General, please remove your sword
장군도 칼을 치우시오
How dare you
이놈이.…
Byuljang, arrest these men at once
별장! 놈들을 당장 결박하라
Now
어서!
Look here
다 보시우!
How about having captain Daejung as our leader from now on?
이제부터 진립형님이 우릴 이끌면 어떻겠수?
That's only way to reach the castle won't we?
그래야 토성까지 살아 갈 수 있지 않갔어?
Dochoong
도충
General...
장군님!
Pass your authority to Daejung
토성까진 진대정에게 행군을 맡기십시오
Do you think you came here by yourself?
너희들 힘으로 여기까지 왔다고 생각하나?
under this hard situation
고통스러운 상황이 올 때마다
Someone had to make tough decisions
장군으로서 얼마나 어려운 결정을 내려야 했는지
Do you know that?
너희들이 알고 있어?
I made these decisions on behalf of the group
누군가는 힘든 결정을 내려야 했어
From now on, whoever bothers my way I will cut your throat under the name of the king
이후로 나와 마수치는 자는 국법에 따라 목을 칠 것이다
General, you are still in recovering---
장군님 아직 몸이 불편하십니다
Don't You are the one who I want to kill most
지금 내가 제일 베고 싶은 놈이
It's you
바로 너야!!
Why don’t you anyone detain the general?
왜 아무도 붙잡지 않죠?
General, come back
장군 돌아와요
You may lead these poor people, but that doesn't change our situation
자네가 이 불쌍한 중생들의 우두머리가 돼도 달라질건 아무것도 없어
Do you think these all happening caused because of him?
한 사람의 잘못으로 이 지경이 됐다고 생각하나?
lam not bright enough to know the future
전 결과를 미리 알고 행동 할 만큼 똑똑하지 못합니다
You should have hold onto the general
자년 장군을 붙잡아야 했어
The only thing I desire most is for us all to go home
제 바램은 우리 모두가 고향으로 돌아가는 검니다
We must leave this place
어서 여길 떠나야 해
Your highness, did you have a nightmare?
공주님 악몽을 꾸셨나요?
The clay fortress is not too far away We should prepare to leave
여긴 토성이 얼마 남지 않았어 어서 떠나자
But your highness, everyone is asleep
공주님 모두 잠들었습니다
Don't worry too much
너무 염려마십시오
He couldn't have gone too far
멀리 가진 않았을 검니다
Even if he desired to come back he is a person who would never do so
돌아오고 싶어도 그러지 못하는 분이네
This is Princess BuYong
난 명황실의 부용공주다
chased by YUAN, lam heading to the clay fortress
원군에 쫓겨 해안토성 위해로 가고 있다
Send the soldiers there immediately
즉시 군사를 보내라
Wehae!
위해!
We will go around the forest
숲을 돌아서 추격한다
We cannot sir
안됩니다
If we don't chase them now we will lose them in the woods
지금 추격하지 않으면 숲에서 놓칠 검니다
Their destination is where the forest ends
숲이 끝나는 곳에 그들의 목적지가 있어!
I vowed never to return without capturing the princess
난 공주를 잡아 가겠다고 맹세했다
we've all prepared to death when we've started the battle
어차피 죽음을 각오한 싸움이다
The Mongolian are not afraid of the death
우리 몽고의 전사들은 죽음을 두려워한 적이 없다
Not afraid of the death
죽음이 두렵지 않습니다
Be careful, you carry with a baby
조심해요. 애기 있잖아요
Thank you
고마워요
Your welcome
천만해요
Daejung
대정
How are the wounds?
상처는 어떻습니까?
the poison in his body is almost neutralized
독은 어느 정도 빠졌네
-Why aren't you helping the general up? - It is not necessary! I can get up by myself
-장군을 일으키지 않고 뭐하나? -됐어 나혼자 일어날 수 있어
General, get up
장군 일어나요
Do not call me a general anymore
절 더 이상 장군이라 부르지 마십시오
Whatever you may say, you are still a general
누가 뭐래도 당신은 장군이예요
You led the group very well. Please go with us
이제껏 당신은 행군을 훌륭하게 이끌었어요
Go with me
같이 가요
A welll
우물이다!!
Where are all the boats?
대체 배가 어디 있다는 겁니까? 예?
What about the MING troops?
군사들은요? 예?
Where is the princess? We came all the way because of that bitch ’s words. Now what?
공주 어디갔어? 그 애미나이 말만 믿고 왔다가 이게 뭘니까?
It's not the princess fault
공주 잘못은 아니야!
Then whose fault is it?
그럼 누구래 잘못입네까?
Was it you?
어! 형님이 젤 먼저 오자했구만 그래
Stop it Who could know this kind happening?
그만혀! 누가 이런줄 알고 온겨?
The YUAN troops will come soon Decide whether we will leave or stay
원군이 곧 오네 먼저 여길 떠날지 있을지를 정하게!
Let's leave this place
여길 떠납시다
Close the gates
성문을 닫아!!
Go get a bar
빨리 빗장할 걸 찾아와
Hurry
어서 서둘러라
Call a man who can speak KORYO
고려말을 하는 병사를 불러라
Listen! For years, KORYO has been the vassal of the Great WON Empire
고려인들은 들어라 고려는 오랫동안 대원의 신하국이었다
If you hand over the princess, we will let you all live
주원장의 여식을 당장 내 놓으면 모두 살려주겠다
Daejung, we are out matched
대정, 우리의 숫자론 저들을 막아낼 수 없네
The princess is
형님 이제 공주는
none of our business any more
우리하고 아무상관도 없지 않소
What they want is me
저들이 원하는건 나예요
You have escorted me here, $0 you kept your promise
당신들은 이미 약속을 지켰어요
You don't need to sacrifice people anymore for me
더 이상 날 위해 희생을 할 필요는 없어요
If you refuse to hand her over,
만일 공주를 내놓지 않으면
we will destroy you all
너희들을 몰살 시킬 것이다
Daejung, you must decide
대정이 결정을 내리게
Help us
도와주시오
Uh? The gates are opening
성문이 열려요!
the great fighter is still alive
창잡이가 살아있었군
He ruins everything
저놈이 일냈구만 일냈어
Those who wish to leave may do so Those who wish to stay, may stay
떠날자는 떠나고 남을 자는 남는다
Honey, honey
여보! 여보!
Pitch the tents. We will prepare the battle
파오를 세워! 전쟁을 시작한다
father
아버지는요?
What the hell are you doing?
누가 너더러 그러짓을 하라고 했어?
Daejung, Daejung I found the bamboos
대정, 내성 뒤에서 대나무를 찾았소
Hey, Go away Go away
야, 저리들 안가? 저리가 저리가
You look still pale
몸도 안좋은데
I'm alright ! wanna help you
괜찮아요. 저도 돔고 싶어요
Water! Water comes!
물이 나와유!
Here is water Come here
물이에요. 빨리 와보세요
water comes
-물나와 물이 나와 -물 나와요
so happy
하하하하.…
Their attacking skills are speedy and quick
원군의 공성술은 빠르고 신속하죠
First, they will attack the gate Then will be surround it and climb up
아마도 성문을 집중 공격하다 일시에 에워싸며 오를겁니다
It is a very difficult situation
성벽같은 곳은 매우 불리하죠
General, please lead us
장군님께서 지휘해 주십시오
I don't want to become a fool again
다시는 우스운 꼴을 당하고 싶지 않아
Everybody knows, the KORYO troops are outstanding the protecting skills for the castle
수성전은 고려병사만큼 잘 싸우는 자들이 없다 하죠
But it is because they had excellent leaders
그건 항상 훌륭한 장수가 전투를 이끌었기 때문입니다
General!
장군님!!
I will fight by myself
나혼자 싸울거야
I was the one who made us head to KORYO
애초에 고려로 가기로 한 것도
and save the princess I started everything
공주를 구한것도 모두 내가 시작한 일이니까
Whether we go home or fight for a name
고향에 가는거든 명분을 위해서는
this is the time for all of us to unite
힘을 합쳐야 할 때입니다!
It is none of your business
너희완 상관없어
This is my war
이건 내 전쟁이니까
Distribute liquor to the soldiers and let them sleep until the sun is fully up
병사들에게 술을 나뉘주고 폭 자게 해
We have to capture the princess and return to the base as soon as possible
빨리 공주를 잡아 돌아가야합니다
For the past three months, we haven't been rest for a single day
지난 석달간 하루도 편히 쉬지 못했어
We need to attack them as quickly as we can! What if the MING troops come...
어서 끝내야죠 만약 명군이 들이닥치면
Here is only two They and us
여긴 아무도 없어. 시간은 충분하다
How many one can be alive among us?
우리 중에 몇 명이나 살아남을까?
stay with me
내 옆에만 있어
Wow! Thank you brother
우와! 형 고마워! 이야!
it is relatively safe at the coast and sides of the castle Let's protect the front
해안과 양옆은 비교적 안전하니 우린 전면을 방어합니다
Monk, take care of the princess and the elderly people
스님은 내성에서 공주와 노약자를 돌보시고
The Interpreter and I will take care the central gate
나와 역관이 중앙을
you and Dochoong in the east
별장님과 도충이 동쪽을
- Yeosol and HA-II will protect in the west.... - Dochoong and I will cover the east
-여솔과 하일은 서쪽을.… -나와 도충이 동쪽을 지키겠네
what about me, sir?
대정님 저는요?
Dansaeng has something to do
단생이 너도 할 일이 있어
Never come out, never! You hear?
가만히 가만히
Stay there
절대 밖으로 나오지마!
You'll be in big trouble if you make one move
여기서 움직이면 아저씨한테 혼나
if you come out---
나오기만 해봐라! 곽
Pul
당겨
Wow, you've made the spares a lot
어유! 많이 만들었네
Huh? They start to move...
저것들이 올라나보네
Dochoong, don't shoot your arrows without my signal
도충 내가 신호 할 때까지 쏘면 안돼
Wait until they come closer
더 가까이 올때까지 기다려
Shoot!!
싸라!!
The YUAN troops are coming
원병이 왔다!
Sit down
당황하지 말고 조용하시오!
Cut the ropes
출을 잘라라!
Attack
공격해라!
Don't retreat! Keep your place
자기자리를 지켜라 물러서지마라
Bring all the shields Break the fortress gate Go!
방패를 모아라.
Daejung, Hurry up
대정 빨리 서두르게
General, the messenger has arrived
장군님 전령이 왔습니다!
Stop the attacking
공격을 멈춰라
We received orders to withdraw. Shit
철수 명령이다
We almost win What the hell---
다 이겼는데 후퇴라니… 젠장.…
Kill them all
숙여버릴테다
Saori... Saori
샤오리… 샤오리!!
Look over there A white flag at the YUAN's side
저길 보게 원군 진영에 흰기가 올랐네
It is to mourn the death of someone in high position
신분이 높은 자를 애도하는 거야
If they attack once again
만약 저들이 다시 전면 공격을 해 온다면
It will be difficult for us to beat them
막아내기 힘들겁니다
General! why did you order us to withdraw?
장군님! 왜 철수시켰습니까?
Dig deep wells in the middle of the hill
비탈 중간에 우물을 깊이 파라
We almost win...
함락 직전이었습니다
Cookoo has passed away
쿠쿠님이 돌아가셨다
at right after we left headquarters
우리가 본진을 떠난 직후에
Held memorial ceremony, first Then, we will resume our attack
먼저 제를 올린 뒤에 다시 공격한다
Why did you leave your place!
왜 성곽을 지키지 않았어!
Because of you, So many people died
니가 자리를 띠 때문에 이 많은 사람들이 죽었잖아!
Stop chanting that It is making people angrier
기딴 거 치치마슈 더 화만 돋구지 말구!
Stop crying Anyway, we've beaten the enemy
그만 울어라. 어픈 적을 물리졌어
Your family is like the loyalist to the MING Empire
너희 가족은 황실을 위해 충성을 바졌다
The Emperor will award you greatly
나중에 큰상을 내리마
Award? Hey, who made us
상이라고?
come all the way over here?
누구때 우리가 이꼴이 됐는데.…
First killed my husband and now it is my daughter---
니가 내 서방 잡아먹고 이젠 딸년마저.…
How dare you speak like so to the princess
아니…….감히 공주님한테
You go! Then, we're all safe
너만 나가면 우린 다 안전할거야!
Because of you, we all die like dogs
너 하나 때문에 다 개죽음 당할거야
Byuljang!
별장!
What the hell are they doing?
대체 무슨 짓을 하려는 거지?
The water channel is blocked
물길이 막혔는데
Everything will be over by tomorrow
내일이면 결판나겠군
Cookoo started a losing war
결국 우린 명나라를 이길 수 없어
The dreams of the great Ghengis Khan
위대한 징기스칸 꿈은
may fade away forever
여기서 끝나버릴지도 모른다
Don't say. Your words have
그런 나약한 말을 하시면
great influences on the fighting sprits
병사들의 사기가 떨어집니다
Let's return to the prairies
조원으로 돌아가자
You mean we should just leave like this?
이대로 돌아가자는 검니까?
We are taking the princess with us
공주는 반드시 데려간다
The children are waiting for you
아이들이 자네를 찾고 있네
Why did they find me?
개들이 왜 날 찾아요?
I have no business with them, right?
난 개들하고 아무상관 없습니다
It is not your fault to avoid a battle
자네가 싸움을 피하는 건 잘못된 일이 아니야
You told me
나더러
that I was irresponsible, didn't you?
책임지지도 못하는 일을 맡는 인간이라고 하셨죠?
You were right
맞습니다
lam-- mean and coward
애들만도 못한 아수 비겁한 인간이죠
In this situation, it is more difficult for one not to fight than to fight
이런 상황에선 싸우는 것보다 싸우지 않는 것이 더 어렵지
If you disagree a useless cruelty, keep the conviction
살생을 피한다는 신념이 있고 그것을 끝까지 지켜낸다면
I think that is courage too?
그거야말로 더 큰 용기가 아니겠는가?
At one time
한 때는
Il was a student of Confucianism, dreaming of the righteous world
왕도정치를 꿈꾸는 바른 유생이었어요
But for a countryman like me
근데 나 같은 지방향리 출신은
I was not even given the chance to apply for a position of government official
아예 관직 근처에도 못가겠더라구요
That is why I joint this journey
그래서, 이렇게
which no one else want to go
남들 안가는 사행길에 따라 나선 것도
I wanted to create an opportunity...
입신 할 기회를 찾으려 그런건데.…
l always end up with bad luck...why?
왜 난 항상 일이 잘 안 풀리는지 모르겠습니다
Pray for a hundred days to Buddha
백일기도를 해 보게나
He will help you
부처님께서 많이 도와주실걸세
Does it really work?
정말 효험이 있답니까?
Aren't you going to the children?
아이들한테 안 가 볼텐가?
She is giving birth!
아이를 낳으려고 해요
We need hot water-- What shall we do?
더운 물이 없는데.…… 어떡하죠?
We don't even have drinking water
담답하긴… 먹을 물 조차 거의 없어
What the hell you guys all doing here
남자들이 여기서 뭘 하는거예요?
Get out, get out
어서 나가요 빨리!!
Isn't that Dansaeng? Where is he going?
어데 가는기여?
That son of bitch He is out of mind
저 아 새끼. 저거이 정신 나갔구만
Dansaeng!
저 단생아
Call the people
사람들 좀 불러와
I'll go and get him
내 가보고 올텐께
What can we do?
야 야 조심하라우!
shit, be careful
적이야!
Here is thieves
놈들을 붙잡아라
General, two men stole water from our well
장군님 두놈이 물을 홈졌습니다
What about Dansaeng? Where is he?
단생이는 어더요?
Uh? He were right behind
금방 쫓아왔었는디
Where is he? Uh, over there
워이? 어, 저기
Dansaeng!
단생아
Dansaeng stnad up
단생아 일어나
Give me that
주십시오
Dochoong
도충
throw the fire
던져라
-Dansaeng -Hurry
-단생 -더 빨리
-Run! Run!
-빨리 -날래 뛰라우 날래 뛰어
-Almost... -Climb up
다왔어 다왔어 그래 올라와 빨리
Get the rope
출을 잡어
Climb up! Climb up
야 새끼야 너부터 먼저 올라오라우!
Dansaeng
단생!
Hurry up
빨리 올라와 임마
Wait
잠깐만요
what the hell he's doing?
단생아 야! 야
Dansaeng, come back
단생 돌아와!
Come on. Hurry up
야! 빨이 와! 임마
Get this one first
받아요
Hurry up
빨리 올라와
pretty clever Do you want to try?
제법 영리하군 너도 해볼테나?
Dansaeng. That's alright Give me your hand
단생아 괜찮아 손을 줘
No+>
안돼!
Dansaeng
단생아
Shit Stop crying
이 쌍놈의 새끼 울긴 와우네 울지말라우!
Let him cry
울게 뇌뒤라
How dare you come here, huh?
뭔 낮짝으로다 왔어? 응?
You want to kill all, huh?
우리 다 지면 곡해줄라고 왔어? 응?
Dochoong!
도충아!
Then, give me back my eye! Give me
기전에 내 눈깔부터 내라우! 내눈깔 내라우 내눈깔!!
Dochoong
도충아!
You told us you would give us a boat, didn't you?
니 처음에 배준다고 그랬었디?
What is the princess of the MING Empire? You even can give us a small boat?
명나라 공주면 깃 배 한 척 못구하네?
Because of your words we come all the way over here
우리는 그것만 믿구 져라고 왔는데
where's the boat? The boat!
배가 어어 배가?
What did you hit me? why? Why me?
와 때리는 검네까? 와때리는검네까? 와요? 와? 와? 뭐
How come you hit me?
헝님이 나 때릴 자격이나 있수?
Then, hit me. Hit me more!
더 때리슈 더 때려 더 때려
Don't blame the princess
공주를 탓하지 마라
Everything was my decision
모든건 내가 결정한 일이니까
The general will take responsibility?
장군이 책임진다구요?
How do you take responsibility for the situation like this?
이런 상황을 어떻게 책임진다는 검니까?
We just have to send the princess out alone Why can't we do so?
공주 혼자만 나가면 되는걸 와 못하는 검네까?
Why?
와요?
Why don't you sent her out?
때문에 못하는검네까? 때문에
Let me go, you son-of-a-bitch
뇌 이쌍놈아 새끼야!!
Someone has to tell the princess about this
누구라도 나서서 공주한테 애기를 해야 되는거 아닙니까?
Just shut up
조용히 하란 말이야
Daejung! Don't stop them It's better them to say what's on their minds
대정! 저들의 말을 막지 말게 하고 싶은 말은 하는게 좋아
General, what are they talking about?
장군, 지금 무슨 말 하고 있죠?
You are all cowards
너희들 모두 비검한 놈들이야
Then, let's just cut the princess head off
그럼 차라리 공주의 목을 칩시다!
You keep out of this
넌 나서지 마라
If we hang her head outside the fortress wall, they might turn back
성 밖에 목을 걸어두면 놈들이 돌아갈지도 모르지
If you all wish, I'll do that
원한다면 내가 하겠소
interpreter, what's Yeesol saying?
여솔이 뭐라고 했지?
Tell me! I order
말해 여솔이 뭐라 했어?
That you should be sent to the enemy
공주님을 성밖으로 나가게.…
Shuts your mouth
입닥쳐!!
Then, do you want me to tell her that he offered to cut her head off?
그럼 목을 치자는 얘길 해주라는 겁니까?
Do you know that your words make her hurt a lot?
니가 한 말이 공주한테 얼마나 큰 상처가 되는지 알아?
I came all the way here for only her
내가 여기까지 온 건 오직 한 사람 때문이야!
Never wish for something you can never get
넘 볼 수 없는 것을 넘보지 마라!
Don't forget you are a slave
니가 노비란걸 잊지마
Have you ever heard of the slave, Manjuk?
어릴 적 만적이란 노비 얘길 들었지
He said, People are all the equal
사람이면 본디 다 같은 사람이지
Is there any special blood for king or others?
왕후장상의 씨가 따로 있겠느나고 했어
After saying those words, he were hanged
그자는 그 말을 내밸고 참수 당했다
Whoever aims at my neck will be cut off his arm first
누구든 내목에 칼을 겨누기 전에 그 팔이 잘라질 걸.…
My sword carries no mercy
내 검은 자비심이 없어
Do you want to match?
해 볼까?
Too many have died so far, too many--
그동안 우린 너무 많이 죽었고 많이 죽였어
Now you want us to kill each other?
이젠 우리끼리 죽이자는 건가?
whatever happens do me Don't help me
앞으로 어떤 일이 있어도 절대로 날 돕지 마라
It's a boy!
낳았어요 고추예요!
the princess Bless the child
공주님! 축복 해 주십시오
for luck and health
앞으로 씩씩하게 살라고 말입니다
What are you doing here?
명감 무슨 쓸데 없는 짓이예요!
Are you planning to freeze him?
애를 얼어죽게 할 작정이유?
She's always take care of herself, she doesn't deserve to do that
축복할 자격도 없는 인간이야
Hurry and take the child inside
빨리 애데리고 들어가자고
Before he catches cold
감기 걸리기 전에 어서
Your highness
공주님
forgive me
죄송합니다.…
Bring me a horse
말을 가져와
lam leaving this fortress
토성을 나가겠어
Stop this, your highness You are the reason we fight for up to now
우리가 그동안 싸운 이유가 뭐였습니까?
As you all watch, everybody hope me to leave this place as soon as possible
모두 내가 빨리 나가길 바라고 있어
As a princess of the Great MING Empire I will end this war with my own hands
대명의 공주답게 내 손으로 전쟁을 끝내겠어
Your highness, please don't go Please
공주님 나가지 마세요 제발.…
Do you want me to take my own life right here?
여기서 죽는 걸 보겠느나?
No one may step forward
아무도 나서지마
I will go by myself
혼자 나가겠다
General...
장군님!
Get out of my way
비켜!
The KORYOs wont give up you, your highness
고려인은 끝까지 공주님을 지킬검니다
Please trust me!
저를 믿어주십시오
How dare you block me?
누가 감히 내 앞을 가로 막느냐
Wait for her they are coming towards us
서둘지 마라 이리로 오고 있다
You can't go
가면 안돼
Will you watch guard outside the fortress?
성밖을 보고 있어주겠나?
Kill him!
죽여라
Wait
멈춰!
Let him pick up the sword
무사에게 검을 잡을 수 있게 해라
What happened others?
별장은 어떻게 됐나?
What about Yeesol?
여솔인?
Just stay where you are
그냥 계십시오
Daejung, Daejung
성님!성님! 올라와보슈!
You can't move sir, not now
움직이면 안돼유 지금.…
can't move
안돼는디.…
The royal castle was too suffocating for me
황궁이 너무 답답했어요
I thought that if I left there I would be free
무작정 밖으로 나오면 자유로워질거라 생각했죠
This is all my fault
이렇게 된 것도 다 내 잘못이죠
I'm so scared
너무 무서워요
I don't think I can bear it any longer
더 이상 견더낼 자신이 없어요
So do I lam also a coward
나도 검쟁이입니다
I was always afraid
남들이 그걸 알아차리지나 않을까
that people would notice that
그게 더 두려웠죠
I do not deserve being called general
장군이라 불릴 자격도 없습니다
Everyone come here
어서들 와보라우!!
He may die
죽었나봐요
He moves...
움직여유.…
His life is long enough...
아새끼래 명이 길구만.…
General, what is the meaning of this?
장군님 대체 왜 이런 짓을 해야합니까?
When they open the gate doors to rescue him, we'll easily enter the fortress
저들이 문을 열고 구한다면 그 때 공격한다
If they decide not to come out for him then I will be able to acquire a great warrior
구하지 않는다면.… 난 뛰어난 무사를 얻을 수 있어
Is there anyone who save him?
어서 누구든 내려가봐요!
-I'll go down to get him -General
- 내려가서 구해오겠어! -장군
if we open the door now we'll all die
지금 문을 열면 모두 죽습니다
It's the enemy's trap
적의 유인책입니다
Then you're saying we just stand back and watch?
가만히 보고만 있자는건가?
That's better idea!
잘 생각했수다!
Let's just kill him with our own hands
차라리 우리 손으로 죽입세다
Should I throw the torch?
햇불 던집네까?
The moonlight is bright...
달빛이 밝아!
Daejung... Daejung
대정!
Don't shoot
쏘지마세요!
You like him too don't you?
당신도 그를 좋아하잖아요
Daejung
대정
Do you still consider me general?
아직도 날 장군이라 생각하나?
I want to lead the battle at tomorrow
내일의 전투를 내가 지휘하고 싶네
Until now we have gone through so much
그동안 너무나 많은 고난을 겪었습니다
It is a miracle that we've made it so far
우리가 여기까지 온 것만 해도 기적이죠
However
하지만
according to the Chinese proverb
행생불생, 필사불사라 했소
if we attempt to live, we die, and if we attempt to die, we live
살고자하면 죽을 것이요 죽고자하면 살 것이라
Let us trust each other, and unite
서로 힘을 모읍시다
Even if we all die---
설령 죽음에 이를지라도…
Tomorrow they will break the gate and enter
틀림없이 내일은 성문을 부수고 들어 올 겁니다
If they come in we will use these bomb!!
안으로 들어오면 이걸 터뜨릴 검니다
Be careful
괜찮습니다 연결하십시오
Come here...
자 이쪽으로.…
All stand up
모두 일어들나게
Tomorrow, we will protect you, your highness
내일은 저희가 공주님을 지킬 겁니다
Do you wish to become a general of the Great YUAN Empire?
대원제국의 장수가 되지 않겠나?
lam a free man Kill me
난 자유인이다 죽여라!
They never took your existence seriously
고려인들은 처음부터 널 원하지 않았어
In order to rebuild the Great YUAN Empire we need courageous warriors like you
대원제국을 다시 세우려면 너 같이 용맹한 무사가 필요하다
A the morning mountain at home, white bird sing a song x
겨단풍이 붉게 물든 숲 하얀 새가 노래하네
i l want to hear the song, wish to go back home
껴하얀새의 노래하는 그곳이 나의 고향
Sir, you resemble my father who had passed away
어른은 제 아버님과 많이 닮으셨습니다
The KORYOs and the HAN's look very much alike We're like brothers
고려족과 한족은 원래 비슷하지
We're like brothers
우린 형제 같은 사이야
We have dragged on this too long
전쟁을 끝낸다
everyone will die
모두 죽인다
Before sunset comes we return to the prairie
해가 지기전에 초원으로 돌아간다
No, no, wait a minute
잠깐만유!
Fire, fire, fire! They use fire first
불이야! 불! 불이야!
Don't move
움직이지마
Everyone run for cover
었드려!
General
장군님
we've failed
실패입니다
Daejung....
대정
I always want to have an honorable death
난 명예롭게 죽고 싶었다
That's my dream
그게 내 꿈이었어
Jaosinwe! Jaosinwe!
짜오신위! 짜오신위!
We must go out and fight together!
모두 나가 함께 싸우자
Dochoong!!
도충아!
Protect the princess Go out this fortress with her
공주를 데리고 성밖으로 나가시오 어서!
So many warriors have died because of you!
너 때문에 너무 많은 사람들이 죽었어
Yesol...
여솔.…
It's too dangerous
진립 너무 위험해요
You cannot cross the sea with that boat
저 배론 바다를 건널 수 없어요
I must go
그래도 가야합니다
Only those who have a long journey will see the long roads to go home
길을 떠나온 자만이 그 아득한 먼 길을 보게 된다